(arrows whooshing)
(ominous music)
(ocean droning)
(ominous music continues)
(water sploshing)
(indistinct radio chatter)
(ominous music continues)
(phone clicks)
(Hazmat Worker) Dr. Goldstein,
Rover 7 made it back
to the surface, it seems
to be working.
Everything's been recorded.
It can't be left alone.
(ominous music rising)
(celestial music)
(button clicks)
(projector whirring)
We found them.
(celestial music rising)
(text whirring)
(soft celestial music)
Ah, Mr. Peters,
there's someone waiting
for you in your office.
Waiting for me?
James Peters?
I'm sorry, do I know you?
I'm Dr. Julia Goldstein.
I work for the
Pickman Corporation.
(soft celestial music continues)
It's inspiring to see
you've been following
in your father's footsteps.
A researcher.
Must be in the blood.
I'm sorry, but I'm
not interested
in any more talks or
lectures about my dad.
I've written just about
everything there is to know,
so buy my books, I do my
own research now.
I know.
The Miskatonic
astrobiology program,
partially funded by us.
Look, I'm not interested
in any more handouts
from the Pickman Corporation.
(sighs) Mr. Peters,
what if I were to tell you
that Pickman is
selecting candidates
for some new research?
An expedition.
One might say it's an
astrobiologist's
dream come true.
An expedition?
Our teams have been doing
research in the Antarctic
and Southern Atlantic oceans
for the past seven years,
until a few months ago when
we found something unexpected.
(soft celestial music continues)
(laptop whirrs)
Our team mapped a trench in the
Antarctic continental shelf,
west of the Mid-Atlantic Ridge
between South America
and Antarctica.
We've collected over 12,000
square kilometers of data,
and we found a new
deepest point in the ocean
of 37,000 feet.
How can that be possible?
We knew that the continental
shelf was unusually deep,
but it was something
else, on the ocean floor,
that, uh, caught us by
surprise, shall we say.
(soft celestial music continues)
This is footage from a
remote control sub
we sent down there.
What is that?
It looks almost man-made.
Well, we have a theory that
it's some kind of portal.
To where?
That, Mr. Peters, is what
we're going to find out.
Pickman wants you to
join the expedition team.
I have some people I'd
like you to meet.
(text whirring)
Thank you, everyone, for
attending at such short notice.
You're finally about to
see why this interruption
to your busy lives is
so very worth your time.
I'll make the introductions.
This is Gordon Atkins,
head of the manned
submersibles laboratory
at London's Royal Society for
Improving Natural Knowledge.
Uh, he's agreed to lead
our expedition,
and is by far the most
qualified man for the job.
Christine Harris,
marine biologist
and member of the European
Marine Biology Symposium.
James Peters is developing
our discovery programs
at the prestigious
Miskatonic University
and is something of an
expert in the field
of Pickman Corp's
early research.
Joseph Meeker is our safety
and communications officer.
And finally, Hank O'Connell,
our lead engineer.
Hank, the floor is yours.
(soft celestial music)
Hello, everyone.
I'm really very pleased
to meet you, finally.
I expect you will be wondering
what it is I've engineered.
Through the Pickman Corporation,
my team have managed to build
a deep-diving submersible
like nothing that's ever
existed before.
(button beeps)
This is Providence 3.
250 tons, built with
syntactic foam,
capable of withstanding
the huge compressive forces
of the water at 37,000
feet and below.
Impressive, Hank.
Makes you wonder what happened
to Providence 1 and 2 though.
So state of the art
that it can safely
take us into this
ancient opening
in the earth's seabed
hydrosphere.
I'm sorry, into the opening?
Didn't you say you sent
remote operated vehicles
in that never came out?
Oh, yes, some have made it back.
Some?
Listen, we aren't
going to pretend
that this isn't a
risky expedition.
We wouldn't launch Providence 3
with a crew on board if
we weren't 100% certain
our technology was safe.
Test dives have been completed
with highly satisfying results.
Now all it needs is a crew.
What do you expect
us to find down there?
What if there's nothing but
pitch-black, watery abyss?
The ocean is the last
great frontier of our world.
(soft celestial music continues)
Now, I have dedicated
my whole life
to seeking out the unknown and
the incomprehensible,
and this gateway might be my
greatest discovery.
It demands to be explored,
Ms. Harris.
If something built
that structure,
just imagine what might
lie within it.
Secrets of the ocean.
And there is a hidden
world beneath us,
gentlemen, ladies, unseen
by human eyes,
because up until now we
have been unable
to create the technology
necessary to take us there.
Your mission as the crew
of Providence 3
is to be that interface
between our technology
and that new dark continent
we aim to explore.
These files contain the
key data collected so far,
and outline the expedition.
You'll need to complete
two months of training
before the dive.
Read them closely.
You have 24 hours to decide
whether you're in or out.
(soft celestial music continues)
James.
I'm so glad you came.
Walt would be so proud to
see us exploring
the unknown together.
Thank you, Mr. Pickman.
It's a lot to think about.
It is, but I wouldn't want
to make this trip without you,
it wouldn't seem right,
for Walt's sake.
I need you there.
I've been counting down the days
to finally meeting in this crew.
We've worked so hard,
overcome so many
challenges to get this far.
All right, who wants
another drink?
- No.
- Ooh, yes, please.
- Yeah? Gotcha.
- Thank you.
Well, I don't think
we'll be eating like this
at the bottom of the ocean,
so I'm gonna enjoy it
while I can.
(Hank laughs)
You up for it then?
What, a voyage the deepest part
of the planet
anyone's ever been?
How could I walk away from that?
Aah, there's nothing to beat it,
being out there in the deep sea.
Firsthand research, it's
what we're born to do, right?
You know, I just,
I can't comprehend
the water pressure at
30,000 feet or whatever.
Weight of an entire
ocean pressing down on you.
If anything goes wrong.
All right, now I'm worried.
You now, you're putting
your life in my hands.
Very capable hands, though.
Okay, here we go. (groaning)
- Cheers, team.
- (Team) Cheers.
It's not really what we were
designed to do though, is it?
- It sounds risky.
- Ah, expect the unexpected...
First rule of deep
sea exploration.
Wow, well, we'll all sleep
better tonight knowing that.
Thank you, Gordon.
You've done this before then?
Ah, many times.
Never this deep though.
We'll be setting a new record.
Everything you do is five
times harder in the ocean, okay?
Just remember that.
But you're still going
along with it, all of you?
Well, look, it's like
the old man said,
"It is the chance of
a lifetime."
Well, team, to Providence 3.
(Team) To Providence 3.
Guys, I need some fresh
air, I'll be right back.
Hm, do you want me to
get you another drink?
No, no, I've had enough, really.
Sorry. Ex-excuse me.
(soft celestial music)
Hey, you okay?
Um, doesn't it scare you at all?
Um, I don't know.
I have this, um,
respect for the ocean.
I mean, it's my life,
but I know it can turn
on you in a heartbeat.
So you think the others
know who you are, Peters?
Or they haven't put two
and two together yet?
So you noticed?
Yeah.
I mean, obviously I
had to research Pickman
when Dr. Goldstein contacted us,
you know?
See what he's into. His history.
What was it like growing up
around something like that?
I mean, the stories and,
and the legends,
and all the theories.
I'd rather just
have my dad back.
You mean they really
never found him?
That wasn't some hook
just to sell more copies?
Gone without a trace.
I'm sorry.
Hey, it's okay.
Um, it was a long time ago.
(soft celestial music continues)
Look, Jim, I don't
think they would
send us down there and
spend all this money
if they weren't certain there
was more for us to discover.
What you think there's
something they're
not telling us?
If I go on this expedition,
I need to know that
I'm coming home.
This is my son.
He's, um, he's seven months old,
and I'm all he is got.
My parents are
looking after him.
And what's he called?
Sam.
Uh, look, I, I know what a
huge sacrifice I'll be making.
I mean, with the, with
the training and,
and the trip, and the time
away from him is gonna kill me,
but if everything goes to plan,
I'll be back before his
first birthday and...
Maybe I can live with that.
And what if it
doesn't go to plan?
Something tells me
these things rarely do.
(soft celestial music continues)
(text whirring)
(wind gusting)
(soft celestial music)
- Mr. Pickman.
- Thank you.
You all ready there, Jim?
I can't say I slept
much last night.
Just goin' over and over
everything, you know?
Everything that could go wrong.
That's normal, Jim.
You know shouldn't
smoke so much, Captain.
It increases anxiety
and tension.
I like to be tense, dear.
It keeps the senses sharp.
You wanna ciggy, Jim?
Nah, no thanks.
- You wanna dramamine?
- Ooh, you have some?
Hey, uh, how far are we goin'?
(Hank) You'll see.
She's out there waiting for us.
(boat engine idling)
(soft celestial music continues)
(boat engine whirring)
(submersible droning)
(soft celestial music)
(Rachel) Command Center,
standby,
we are awaiting crew's
arrival at Providence 3.
(buttons clicking)
Morning, Dr. Goldstein.
How long?
We are launching in one hour.
Weather conditions are
looking perfect
for another cup of hours.
Where's our feed?
P3 rear cam one and
rear cam two,
we have a clear signal.
P3 front cam is live.
And the rover cameras will
be activated upon launch.
We're all set for them.
(soft celestial music continues)
Crew approaching P3.
Commence launch operation
in T minus 12 minutes.
Standby for entry.
(hatch thuds)
(water splashing)
(footsteps clacking)
(soft celestial music)
Welcome to Providence.
Okay, team, let's go, go, go!
We've got 20 hours of
life support!
It takes one hour and 30
minutes to get to the seabed.
Let's not waste any oxygen.
Chris.
(soft celestial music continues)
(keypad beeping)
(door hissing)
(soft mystical music)
(soft mystical music rising)
Man, oh, man, this is
not a simulation anymore.
(mystical music continues)
(monitors beeping and whirring)
(switches clicking)
You ready to pilot that thing,
Jimmy?
I have a dreadful
feeling I'm looking
at my own very expensive coffin.
What, two months training
wasn't enough for you?
You're collecting rock
samples, not landing on Mars.
What's the difference?
This is Providence 3
to DP control.
How do you copy, over?
We're receiving you
loud and clear, P3.
Okay, you have a good
comms voice here.
Is that you, Ms. Rachel?
How's it looking out there,
Gordon?
(switches pinging)
Life support's good,
O2 level's good.
Oh, we're groovy.
Apart from the fact
there's 1000 horrible ways
to die down here at the
bottom of the ocean,
we're feeling pretty
great about it.
(soft celestial music)
Okay, Mr. Pickman?
More than okay.
She's remarkable.
(ladder thudding)
(hatch clanking)
(soft celestial music continues)
Hatch is secure, Captain.
Roger that, Hank.
(console beeps)
Be advised, we are in position
and go for launch ops.
Three minutes to commence
launch operation, over
Roger that, DP control.
I'm gonna open the vent.
We are clear to vent.
Opening now.
(soft celestial music rising)
(submersible droning)
(submersible rumbling)
(monitors beeping)
(submersible rumbling continues)
(soft celestial music rising)
(door hissing)
(soft suspenseful music)
Don't worry.
If it buckles, the
whole thing will implode
at hypersonic speed,
and we'll be jelly in a
matter of micro seconds.
What?
You won't have time to
even know it's happened.
(door hissing)
(lights clacking)
(soft suspenseful music rising)
(equipment beeps)
Pre-dive safety briefing's
already completed.
(Rachel) All right, P3,
let's do final checks.
(Gordon) Final checks.
Vision one, CO2 is
running at 0.3%.
Scrubber fan is running.
Depth gauge is working.
Compass is working.
Okay, and I think we're ready.
DP control, we are
clear to launch.
Affirmative.
Good luck on your
voyage to the deep, P3.
You have permission to dive.
Copy that.
Heading down.
(submersible rumbling)
(suspenseful music)
Say goodbye to the
surface world.
(submersible droning)
(soft celestial music)
Approaching 20 meters.
Vents are secure.
40 Meters.
(submersible droning)
P3, what's your speed?
Vertical speed, 3.4 knots.
I have good control.
Copy that.
We're losing light already.
Approaching 100 meters.
Okay, team, good job.
Right on course.
(soft suspenseful music)
(submersible droning)
10,500 meters.
Five minutes 'til target depth.
In 400 meters, we've
set a new record.
(alarm wailing)
(air hissing)
The pressure lock.
(soft celestial music)
Once the rover is fully
submerged, we seal you in.
Then we activate the exit doors.
(chains clattering)
Then, you're on your
own out there,
ready to explore the deep.
Just remember you're training.
Piece of cake.
Hank! Jim!
You need to come see this.
(soft celestial music)
- What is it?
- Turn up front spotlight.
(button beeps)
Are you ready to see
this in person?
We're here already?
X coordinates minus 106,
Y coordinates minus 79.
DP control, we have arrived.
(switch clicks)
(light thuds)
(soft celestial music continues)
(submersible droning)
(Rachel) Just keep talking, P3.
We're looking at a
huge carbonate structure,
a circular gateway.
It's unreal.
Yeah, planet earth's butthole,
just where I wanna be.
No volcanic activity
causes this kind of detail.
These rocks were put here.
By what? They're the
size of houses.
All I know is that this
place will teach us more
than we've ever dreamed.
I'm easing us into the gateway.
Speed is 2.3 knots.
Spotlights are facing forward,
but we're just headed
into absolute darkness.
P3, you must keep talking to us
as you move into the gateway.
The signal is currently
running at 100%.
Everything's stable.
Picture is all good on
front and rear cams.
We're loud and clear.
(soft celestial music continues)
(keypad beeps)
(soft ominous music)
(water trickling)
(submersible rumbling)
(alarm wailing)
Gordon!
- (Rachel) P3?
- Everything's shutting down!
What's going on down there?
I've lost thrusters.
Hank!
P3, come in.
We're losing them.
Try to get a better signal.
I am trying.
(creature screeching)
(suspenseful music)
Activate emergency power!
(switch thuds)
(submersible droning)
(Christine) DP control,
are you reading?
Come in, DP control!
Rachel, can you hear us?
DP...
We've lost them!
Hey, everybody just cool it,
all right?
Gordon, are the thrusters
still malfunctioning?
It's everything, Hank.
Everything has shut down.
We're still sinking.
Depth is approaching
1100 meters.
I'm dropping our weights,
we can't just sit here.
- No, no, stop. Stop!
- Hang on, Gordon, not yet.
Give it a chance.
Remember where we are?
We made it.
- I've gotta find Pickman.
- Wait.
Take this.
I guess we're on our own
down here then.
(submersible droning)
Jesus, Pickman!
(music jolts)
We found them.
(lights click)
(submersible droning)
(console blipping)
All right, we're back on.
(Rachel) P3, do you copy?
Come in P3.
DP control, we copy.
What happened down there?
It looks like we lost power
when we entered the portal.
We've definitely stumbled
on something here.
Three hours of radio silence,
you don't know how glad
I am to hear your voice.
Three hours?
Did she say three hours?
Please repeat, DP control.
How long did you say
we were out of contact?
Three hours and 12 minutes
since your last transmission,
P3.
That's impossible.
Hank, check our life support.
(soft tense music)
(keypad beeping)
Life support has decreased
approximately three hours.
She's right.
What does that mean?
(Cameron) We're not
getting anything up here, P3.
There's disruption on the feed,
a lot of static interference.
Oh my God.
(soft celestial continues)
Describe what we're looking at.
Uh, okay.
Um, I hope you can hear me
clearly enough.
We're, (breathes deeply)
we're drifting above
a huge ancient ruin.
There are decayed stone
structures as,
as big as mountains.
How could there have
ever been life down here?
Sunlight could have
never reached this place.
That implies a whole
new basis of life.
One that doesn't need the sun,
only water.
And darkness.
Maybe it wasn't
always underwater.
There's something on the seabed.
- (Christine) What is that?
- Uh, maneuver the camera.
(stammers) Pan, pan down.
Get a better view of it.
(camera whirring)
(soft celestial music)
Rachel, are you seeing this?
I think I'm getting something.
Look.
Fuck!
That looks like some kind
of life form, doesn't it?
Copy that.
Impossible.
It's definitely some
sort of remains,
buried under centuries
of sediment buildup.
I want to get a
closer look at that.
Where is Mr. Peters?
He's right here.
Peters.
James, I need a tissue sample
from that deep sea organism,
whatever it is, understood?
Copy that.
(soft celestial music continues)
This is the payoff.
The answer to our
deepest wonders.
So many secrets we must know.
It's on you, Jim.
(submersible droning)
(chain clanking)
(water sploshing)
(Jim exhales sharply)
Are you gonna be all right?
Yeah.
(air hissing)
(water sploshing)
(Jim breathing heavily)
(chain clanking)
(switch clicks)
(console blips)
I'll be all right.
(Hank) Repressurizing lock.
Brace for launch, Jim
(alarm buzzing)
(air hissing)
(chains clanking)
(alarm wailing)
(ominous music)
(rover droning)
(chains clanking)
(door creaking)
(door thuds)
(alarm buzzing)
Rover clear for launch.
Opening pressure lock
outer doors...
Now.
(doors whirring)
(rover droning)
(Hank) Launch successful.
You okay?
Just don't let anything
happen to him out there.
Jim, are you receiving?
(Jim) Life support's all good.
There is more current
down here than I expected,
but I've got good control.
Okay, take her down.
All lights facing down.
Increasing vertical
speed to 1.4 knots.
You doing good, Jim.
38,000 feet.
Oh, man, it feels pretty
lonely out here right now.
We're right here with you, Jim.
(chains clanking)
(ominous music)
Guys, are you seein' this?
(dramatic music)
We have a clear image
from all rover cams.
Gently now.
(Jim) 300 units of down thrust.
Take it easy, Jim, you're
right on top of that thing.
Look at that creature.
(celestial music)
Gordon, what was this?
(Gordon) Starboard 20
degrees and ease her down.
(Jim) Whatever this
thing was, it's colossal.
Up close, could have
been as tall
as the Empire State Building.
Okay, Jim, you can't
afford to waste much time.
Get the tissue sample,
get the hell out of there.
Affirmative. I'm in position.
His depth gauge isn't
reading anything,
should we be worried?
(Joe) We haven't got time
to worry. He's doing fine.
(rover whirring)
(Gordon) Nice and easy.
Oh, Jesus, it's like
whale blubber.
Looks like some sort
of cephalopod.
Deep-sea gigantism on
an epic scale.
I can't understand how
it hasn't deteriorated.
Maybe the dissolved
oxygen levels down here?
Makes you wonder how
long it's been dead.
(celestial music jolts)
Guys, check out rear cams,
something moving out there.
- Moving?
- You didn't see it?
I've almost finished
the incision.
I can't see shit out here.
Gordon, I'm picking up movement.
Impossible, nothing
could be alive down here.
- It's reading a life-form.
- It's reading Jim.
This is too big to be
Jim, this is massive!
Well, then it's reading wrong.
Everything's glitching
since we entered the portal.
- Jim needs...
- We don't say anything
until he's got the
sample, he's nearly there.
He might be in danger!
One more minute and
he has got the sample!
He might not have a minute!
Let me talk to him!
- Stop!
- The corporation did
not spend all of this money
for us to come back
with nothing!
Let Jim do his job!
(Jim) All right, guys,
I got it, I got it.
Okay, Jim.
Gordon, please get
him out there.
Is the sample secure, Jim?
Just a little longer.
The sample is secure,
but I've lost my starboard
horizontal thruster.
Guys, I've got a lot of
failures here.
This isn't looking good.
Don't panic, Jim.
(alarm buzzing)
Jim, please respond!
He's not hearing us.
(grunts) Signal's gone.
Hello? Gordon?
(ominous music)
(creature howling)
(ominous music jolts)
(submersible rumbling)
It's moving again,
whatever it is.
(Walt) We've just lost
communication
with port (indistinct).
Something's scrambling
our radios out there.
(ominous music)
(creature howling)
(ominous music rising)
(creature whirring)
- Don't lose him!
- What the fuck is that?
(Gordon) I'm not
going any closer.
We're not leaving without Jim!
Take us down!
Are you insane?
(creature screeching)
(door hissing)
(alarm buzzing)
(Creature) This is
what you wanted, Pickman,
an encounter with the Gods?
Aren't they as
immeasurable as you recall?
(Gordon) DP control,
permission to abort.
(Julia) Permission denied,
Atkins.
Retrieve that rover before
you begin your ascent.
Are you not seeing this?
Permission to abort!
Permission denied, Gordon.
I'm not losing that sample.
(suspenseful music)
(console beeping)
(creature screeching)
Hank, fill the pressure lock,
we're bringing him in now.
(creature screeching)
(Walt) Some strange
electromagnetism in the air.
(creature howling)
- Argh!
- Gordon, take us down!
What is that?
Goddamn it, Gordon,
take us down!
Get out!
No!
I'm taking us down.
No, we're too close!
Fuck!
(creature roaring)
(suspenseful music continues)
(sparks crackling)
(submersible rumbling)
(Christine) Hank, help me!
Christine! (grunts)
(door thuds)
(creature howling)
No!
(suspenseful music)
(Hank grunting)
(sparks crackling)
Christine!
(creature howling)
P3, my thrusters are back.
Your air supply is
not looking good,
get as close to us as you can!
We gotta move!
(creature howling)
(Hank grunting)
(chain clanking)
(creature screeching)
Gordon, I'm heading back!
Jim, prepare to board.
No, no, stop!
Gordon, stop!
Don't open the outer doors!
(suspenseful music continues)
(rover droning)
Christine! She's in the
pressure dock!
- What?
- She's in the water.
Open up the inner doors,
the inner door!
(Gordon) There isn't time!
You'll blast her into the ocean!
She'll die, Gordon! (grunts)
Jim, you'll have to hang on.
(suspenseful music continues)
Christine ah, I'm coming.
(alarm buzzing)
Hurry up!
(chain clanking)
(Hank grunting)
(tense music)
(Joe panting)
(Hank grunting)
(suspenseful music)
No.
No, no.
Come on, gimme a hand!
Help me get her out!
Gordon, the doors
aren't opening.
(creature wailing
and screeching)
Gordon, I'm outside.
Jim, hang in there,
we've got a problem!
Chris is trapped in the
pressure lock!
- What?
- You'll have to wait
for the pressure lock to reseal!
I can't let you in!
(alarm buzzing)
(suspenseful music continues)
- Christine!
- Hank, quick,
Pull her out.
All right.
(Joe grunts)
(ominous music)
(creature roaring)
What the fuck?
(creature howling)
(ceiling crashing)
(water gushing)
(creature howling)
- That's it, grab it.
- Pull up.
Come on, quick. Quick.
(both grunting)
(suspenseful music)
All right, Joe, help her.
Help her? She's fucking dead!
Well do something, you're
the fucking safety officer!
Gordon, I'm closing the
pressure lock.
(alarm buzzing)
(tense music)
(alarm blaring)
(suspenseful music)
(chain clanking)
(hand slaps)
(suspenseful music continues)
(chain clanking)
(door thuds)
(Hank grunts)
(melancholy music)
(Gordon) Hank, we're
taking on water!
The front end is compromised!
Hank, what's going
on down there?
Hank!
Gordon, I think we lost her.
Never mind that, Hank.
Check the bunk rooms.
I'm reading severe
damage down there.
This whole sub is gonna go down
if I don't drop weight now!
(suspenseful music)
(door hissing)
Jim, I'm opening the
outer doors.
Hold on, I'm getting
into position.
(creature roaring)
Fuck!
(Gordon) God, Jim, get
your ass in here now!
(suspenseful music)
(alarm blaring)
Pickman, get up!
Get out of here!
(button clicks)
(keypad beeping)
(door hissing)
(suspenseful music continues)
10 more seconds, Gordon.
Hurry!
(water pattering)
(Hank grunting)
Gordon, the entire bunk
room's flooded.
I'm sealing off this corridor.
Drop weights now or the
water will drag us down!
The pressure doors are
still closing.
Jim's in there!
We don't have time, Gordon!
And we, we can't ascend with
this much water on board!
Gordon!
Five seconds, Hank!
We can wait five seconds!
(suspenseful music continues)
(alarm blaring continues)
It's too late, Jim,
I'm dropping weights.
Hold on!
(switch clicks)
(alarm buzzing)
(creature howling)
(sparks crackling)
(creature screeching)
(suspenseful music continues)
(Jim grunting)
(alarm blaring)
(water pattering)
(Hank grunting)
(Cameron) (indistinct)
does anybody copy?
DB control, we're
leaving the bottom
at X minus 278, Y minus 78!
Is it following you, Gordon?
I don't know! Check the radar!
(button beeps)
No!
No, no, no!
No. (grunting)
(ominous music)
(water pattering)
I can't get the second
door to close!
It's jammed!
Ugh, I can't get out.
Look at it, Hank.
Look at the devastation
they can cause.
Just one of them
against all of us.
- What?
- Our brilliant minds,
totally defenseless
against them.
What are talking about?
They're brilliant, Hank, brilliant.
(Hank moaning)
(alarm blaring continues)
(suspenseful music continues)
(water burbling)
(suspenseful music rising)
No! No!
(ominous music)
No, no, no, no, no!
Why won't you help her?
(Joe whimpering)
Why won't you help, dammit?
(soft music)
Jesus, no.
No!
(Jim grunting)
(palms thudding)
Come on, Chris.
Come on, don't fucking leave
me down here without you.
Come on, please.
(soft music continues)
Come on, come on, come on,
come on.
Come on. Fuck.
Please, Chris. Please.
Come on. Come on.
Breathe, dammit.
Breathe!
Come on, Chris.
Come on.
(Jim grunting and panting)
Fuck.
(Jim panting)
(palms thudding)
Come on.
Come on, come on, just breathe.
Just breathe!
(Christine gagging)
You're all right.
You're all right. (panting)
(Christine) Jim!
(both panting)
You're all right.
(Joe whimpering)
(Jim panting)
(Christine sobbing)
Hey. Hey, it's okay.
It's okay, we made it.
(both shivering)
It's okay. It's okay.
(submersible droning)
Hey.
Yeah, thanks.
(ominous music)
(door hissing)
O'Connell's dead.
See for yourself if you want to,
he's floating in
between the doors.
The whole front of the
sub is underwater.
Are you sure?
Well, unless he went for a swim.
Well, you thought
Chris was dead,
look how that turned out.
Hey, I'm not the one who fell
into the fucking pressure lock.
She wasn't breathing,
how was I to know?
That we should all
just be grateful
that any of us are still alive.
Fuck!
(ominous music continues)
How long till we're back
on the surface, Gordon?
(lighter rasping)
Well, kids, can't say for sure.
We've taken on a fuck
ton of water.
Hank said not to smoke in here.
Do you want one, Jim?
Help yourself.
We'll smoke in his memory.
(soft anxious music)
How long can we survive
like this down here?
We've got three more
hours of life support left.
Can't see it taking us
more than two hours
to get to the surface.
But I can't be sure.
The longer we're down
here, the heavier we get,
the slower we ascend.
Three hours seems tight.
It is tight,
but there's nothing
more I can do about it.
Let's hope there's no
more nasty surprises.
(metal clanks)
(obscure music)
(container thuds)
It's the tissue sample.
(ooze squelching)
(door hissing)
(obscure music continues)
Do you hear them, Jim?
Calling to us...
God's of the deep...
Howling to be perceived
by human minds.
(ominous music)
This tiny specimen,
it's going to change
everything we know.
Everything we ever
thought we knew.
Don't touch it.
We need to get this down
to the lab and isolate it.
Quickly now, before it
deteriorates.
Maybe we should seal
it in the pressure lock.
No, I want this preserved
properly in the lab.
Pickman, this is something
that hasn't been out
of the water for
millions of years,
we have no idea what
we're exposing ourselves
to by bringing this on board.
Ms. Harris, do you
really think you came
all the way down here
just to look at it?
We didn't know we were
collecting living tissue.
So many answers await us, Jim.
I don't have time to waste.
(metal clanking)
(ominous music continues)
(container rasps)
(air hissing)
(tissue squelching)
Careful, Joseph.
(ominous music continues)
Where you going?
We can't stop them
examining that thing,
so someone who knows
what they're doing
should go supervise,
make sure they keep
it contained.
(door hissing)
Three hours, Jim.
I suggest you go with them
and make sure they do
nothing stupid.
I've not seen Pickman
like this since...
A long time.
He's not thinking straight.
I don't know if any of
us are anymore.
(submersible droning)
(Gordon) DP control,
we are a little
under three hours
from the surface.
The tissue sample is
securely aboard.
We've got one casualty.
O'Connell didn't make it.
(obscure music)
(air hissing)
It seems like it's
mostly adipose tissue.
(Christine) Body fat.
This is a big piece you took.
Yeah, no surprise it tried
to knock us halfway
across the ocean.
Totally disconnected
from the body...
But still reactive.
I don't think I've ever
seen anything like it.
Imagine what we could learn
from an organism like this.
The flesh that still lives on
after it's been severed
from the body.
Oh, it still thinks it's
part of the sea beast.
I think that it senses us.
And I say we leave it
the hell alone
and wait 'til it's safely
back at the research base.
Hank built this so we
could do immediate research.
Well, unexpected things
happen when we mess
with stuff we don't understand.
And how do you know this
thing will still be moving,
active, secreting
slime like it is
once we get it back
to the surface?
Guys.
If you don't mind,
I'll take my chances.
Jim.
(flesh squelching)
(tense music)
Whoa.
(flesh squelching)
(tentacle crunching)
(glass squeaking)
Chris, get away from it.
It knows we're here.
Can't we freeze it?
(Joe) I think we pissed
it off enough already.
Pickman, Jim's right.
We need to keep this contained.
We should seal the lab,
we have no idea what
we're dealing with.
I'm paying you to be the
biologist here.
I am not risking someone
else's life for this expedition.
The science trip is over.
Jim, get him out of here and
help me lock this place up.
(Pickman growling)
(tense music continues)
You heard her.
(glass squeaking)
(tentacle squelching)
(keypad beeps)
(door hissing)
(tense music continues)
(tentacle slapping)
(tentacle squelching)
(light switch clicking)
(door hissing)
(tentacle squelching)
(case rasps)
(keypad beeps)
(wound squelching)
(phone ringing)
(ominous music)
(gun snapping)
(ominous music jolts)
(monitor whirrs)
Dr. Goldstein.
Joseph, tell me the
specimen is secure.
It's been contained in
the onboard lab,
Pickman's already running tests.
I think you're gonna be
very satisfied.
I hope so.
Don't underestimate the
value of that tissue sample,
protect it with your life,
because if it doesn't make
it back to the surface...
Lady, if that sample doesn't
make it back, neither do I.
And believe me,
that tuna chunk will be
the least of my worries.
You don't have to worry.
As long as that specimen
is delivered to me,
your safety is guaranteed.
And the deal's the
same as before.
Correct.
Well then, we are
crystal clear, babe.
And I'm already taking
the necessary precautions.
(gun snaps)
Pickman's gonna be pissed.
Pickman isn't
interested in riches.
Well then, his loss is our gain.
(Goldstein) Keep me updated.
(phone call bleeps)
(ominous music)
(ooze squelching)
(keypad beeps)
(door hissing)
(ominous music rising)
(ghostly whispering)
(ominous music continues)
(door hissing)
(ominous music rising)
(ghostly whispering)
(ominous music continues)
(ooze squelching)
(Pickman coughing and wailing)
(flesh squelching)
(soft music)
Something's not right here,
Chris.
There's some strange feeling...
I don't know.
Just try to relax,
it's nearly over.
We've been down here God
knows how long,
and no one's ever
been this deep.
Yeah, but maybe we were
never meant to come here.
You know, maybe nature never
intended us to find this place.
Don't get hysterical on me, Jim.
Have you seen
anything down here?
You know, heard anything?
Things you shouldn't see,
things that couldn't be here?
Like what?
None of this was
meant to be here.
Well, like when you went
into the water,
why did you do that?
Because you saw something, right?
Something made you do it?
No, I fell.
No, you saw something,
you, you, you chased after it,
like, like Sam floating
in the water.
No. Jim, what's
wrong with you?
Look, when I was out there,
I thought I heard my
dad over the intercom.
His tapes, his, his
old recordings,
they were playing at the
bottom of the fucking ocean.
How can that be possible?
Listen to me, you didn't
hear anything, okay?
You panicked.
We're all shocked. It's normal.
I don't think any of
this is normal.
I just know I wanna get home.
We will, but I need you
to keep it together, okay?
I need you.
Help keep me sane until
we're back on the surface.
I can't do this alone.
We came to the bottom
of the ocean,
none of us were ever
entirely sane.
(soft music continues)
You did great out there.
Your dad could never bring
back this physical proof
of things that people
didn't believe existed.
This is gonna shock the world,
Jim.
You lived up to your name.
Yeah, well...
I worry that might not
be a good thing.
We're two hours
from the surface.
Do you copy, DP control?
(buttons clicking)
(console beeping)
Come in, DP control.
(monitor whirring)
(tense music)
(Walt) It's October 25th,
day three of the
Peters-Pickman expedition
to the Antarctic Peninsula.
40 miles into the mountains,
we've uncovered something
extraordinary.
(tentacles squelching)
Can't you hear that?
It's speaking to us...
Communicating.
(creature growling)
(tense music continues)
(Gordon screaming)
What's happening out there?
Wait, Chris! hang on!
(Christine) Come on!
(suspenseful music)
(keypad beeps)
(door hissing)
- Gordon!
(suspenseful music continues)
Christine!
(chains clanking)
(tense music)
(flesh squelching)
Oh my God.
(ooze squelching)
(tense music continues)
(door hissing)
(foot steps clacking)
(tense music rising)
(Pickman screeching)
No!
(water splashing)
Jim, get it open!
(suspenseful music)
I can't.
Get him out of there now!
Hold on.
(door hissing)
(suspenseful music continues)
(ax clanks)
Chris, get out of the way.
(ax clanking)
(Jim grunting)
Come on!
Put down the ax, Jim!
Pickman's in there!
(Joe) That's Pickman's problem.
You're not really gonna
use that thing, Joe.
You open those pressure
doors, this ship fills
with water at a rate
so fucking fast
the liquid will cut your
bodies in two.
Drop it!
(ominous music)
What, you just gonna
let Pickman die in there?
Pickman's lost his fucking mind.
Don't you get it?
This was his dream, to
see those creatures,
those ancient sea gods.
And if that's what he wants,
I do not need to go
down with him.
He didn't even know these
things were down here.
Pickman knew.
He knew what they were,
and he knew they were
only sleeping.
(chuckles) Exactly.
What do you think they
found down in Antarctica?
What do you think they've
been searching
for all these years?
And he just let us wake them up.
Pickman did not spend
all of this money
for you two to have the
adventure of a lifetime.
We were sent here with a
clear objective.
Get the tissue sample
from the fucking water goblins,
make it back to the surface,
and get filthy, fucking rich.
So will you please
both move away
from the fucking pressure doors!
You think that specimen's
gonna make you rich?
It's gonna be harder
than you think.
Oh, you think I'm scared
of a couple of brainiacs?
No, that thing is growing.
You can go and look at it
if you don't believe me.
And I think it's having a
strange psychological effect
on our crew.
Oh, you fucking think.
It doesn't just
exist physically,
it's in our minds,
it's in our thoughts.
Joe, I don't know if
you know this,
but I have a son waiting
for me back home.
He's 10 months old, and if
I don't get back to him,
if I don't see him again,
I swear to fucking God,
you'll die down here with me,
and it won't be pretty.
I don't need to listen
to this bullshit.
(door hissing)
Wait, don't agitate him.
- Jim!
- He's dangerous, Chris.
There's nothing we can do.
(ominous music)
(Gordon coughing and hissing)
(ominous music rising)
(ax rasps)
(eerie music)
(flesh squelching)
(chains clanking)
(Joe grunts and groans)
(Joe moaning)
(bag rustling)
(knife clanks)
(knife rasping)
(Joe moans)
(eerie music continues)
(bag rustling)
(flesh squelching)
(ominous music)
(body crunching)
Gordon?
(Walt) It's from the sea,
frozen in time and
waiting for the thaw.
Jim, my boy, is it really you?
Gordon, maybe you should
come downstairs
and lie down for a while.
I always knew you would
find me one day, Jimmy.
They told me you would come,
but I prayed, I prayed
that it wasn't true.
(Gordon gagging)
(body cracking)
Don't be afraid, Jimmy.
Death is not the end.
These are things I
should never have known,
things of nature never
intended us to find.
Sit down, Gordon.
(Gordon gagging)
I don't think that's
Gordon anymore.
Show them, Jimmy.
Show them the way home,
back to their place
they once knew.
(Gordon gagging)
(body crunching)
None of this insignificant race
will know how I tried
to warn them,
how they left it, too late.
Get the fuck away from me,
Gordon.
Don't make me use this.
When they awake, it
is time for us to sleep.
(Gordon screaming)
(body cracking)
(head whooshing)
(ooze squelching)
(tense suspenseful music)
(both grunting)
(ooze squelching)
(tense suspenseful music rising)
(metal clanks)
(Jim screams)
Jim! (panting)
(suspenseful music)
(Gordon grunting)
(ax thudding)
Gordon!
(alarm blaring)
(ax thudding)
(Gordon grunting)
(suspenseful music continues)
That's it, w-we've lost them.
I can't get a signal,
there's nothing.
(alarm blaring)
(suspenseful music continues)
(door hissing)
(ax thudding)
(Gordon grunting)
Gordon!
(door hissing)
(Gordon grunting)
(alarm blaring continues)
(suspenseful music continues)
Move!
(gun firing)
(Gordon grunts)
(tense music)
Gordon?
(Gordon growling)
(ax clanks)
(alarm blaring continues)
What have you done?
(ooze squelching)
(equipment clattering)
(Joe grunts)
(gun firing)
(bullets thudding and clanking)
Joe, stop, you'll
blow the windows!
Joe, what are you doing?
This thing's going down,
sweetheart,
back down to the bottom
of the ocean,
only I'm not going down with it.
You can't just leave
us to pilot this thing.
Pilot what?
It's scrap metal, lady,
open your fucking eyes!
This thing is going down!
(gun snaps)
(alarm blaring continues)
I'm sorry about your kid.
(suspenseful music)
(ax rasps)
(ax clanks)
(Joe grunts)
(suspenseful music continues)
(gun clanks)
(alarm blaring continues)
Now you wanna fight me now, bitch.
Try it.
(both grunting)
(suspenseful music continues)
(ax thuds)
(flesh squelching)
(flesh tearing)
(ooze squelching)
(both grunting)
(Christine grunts)
(ax thuds)
(Joe laughing)
(suspenseful music continues)
You think we're just
gonna let you walk out
of here, bitch?
No, I don't.
(ax thuds)
(Joe screaming)
(flesh squelching and tearing)
(Joe sobbing)
(obscure music)
(alarm blaring continues)
(Joe moaning)
Jim!
(Jim groaning)
Are you okay?
I'll live.
Okay.
(button thuds)
(alarm buzzing)
Get in the rover,
we've gotta go.
What?
Get in the rover!
- Where's Joe?
- Oh, screw Joe!
Come on, we gotta go!
(chain clanking)
(suspenseful music)
(Joe and Christine grunting)
(Christine panting)
(gun snapping)
(gun firing)
(bullets clanking)
(rover thuds)
(water splashing)
(suspenseful music continues)
(alarm blaring continues)
(water sploshing)
(Christine breathing heavily)
(hatch hissing)
(suspenseful music continues)
(Joe moaning and grunting)
(Joe panting)
(obscure music)
(alarm blaring continues)
(flesh squelching)
(tentacle crunching
and squelching)
(tense music)
(door hissing)
(alarm blaring continues)
Okay, wait for me
here, I'll be a second.
What? Where are you going?
We can't risk someone
else finding it.
You know they'll come looking.
(suspenseful music)
(flare hissing)
(flare bangs)
(door hissing)
(suspenseful music continues)
(keypad beeps)
(door hissing)
(chains clanking)
All right, whatever the
hell you are,
time to make calamari.
(flare whooshing)
(creature screeching)
(fire crackling)
(Jim screaming)
(gun firing)
(suspenseful music continues)
(flesh squelching)
(alarm blaring)
(keypad beeps)
(creature laughing)
(suspenseful music continues)
(Joe) Better hurry, Jimmy.
Five minutes until this whole
thing goes under. (laughs)
This whole things gonna blow
when that door opens. (laughs)
Implode! (laughing)
(keypad beeps)
(door hissing)
(Joe laughing continues)
(fire crackling)
Jim, we don't have
enough air supply.
And that door's set
to open in five minutes.
This whole thing's
gonna implode.
- What?
- One of us needs
to stay behind to seal
the pressure lock.
Go on without me.
No, Jim, we always said we...
Just go!
No, Jim!
(ax clanks)
(suspenseful music)
No!
(ax clanks)
(Joe grunting)
(Joe laughing)
(ax clanks)
You going somewhere?
(Joe grunts)
Jim!
(suspenseful music)
(Joe grunting)
Hey!
(blow thuds)
(Joe grunts)
(both grunting)
(blow thuds)
(Jim screaming)
(Jim groaning)
(suspenseful music continues)
(Joe laughing)
You can't destroy them, Jimmy.
We woke them up,
and now it's all over.
(Joe grunting)
(gun firing)
(Jim screaming)
(Joe thuds)
(suspenseful music continues)
(water pattering)
(ominous music)
(alarm blaring continues)
(ax rasps)
(Joe gasping)
(flesh squelching)
(ominous music rising)
(Joe screaming)
(tentacles squelching)
(Joe grunting)
(Joe screaming)
(gun firing)
(tentacle squelching)
(explosions bangs)
(Jim gasping)
(ominous music)
(fire crackling)
(alarm blaring)
(ax clanks)
(door thuds)
(alarm buzzing)
(outer door whirring)
(ominous music continues)
(water pattering)
(alarm blaring)
(melancholy music)
(Walt) Jim.
Come find me, son.
(water pattering)
(ominous music)
Jim, you came for me.
Let's go together...
Together with them into
the depths of oblivion.
Dad?
(soft music)
(birds squawking)
(medical equipment beeping)
Ms. Harris?
Ms. Harris, can you hear me?
It's okay, you're safe.
We're looking after you now.
Jim?
Providence! (gasping)
They've gone. Ms. Harris.
After communication was lost,
we picked up your rover signal.
They found you drifting.
Your oxygen levels were
dangerously low.
You've been unconscious
for a couple of days.
You killed them.
You knew exactly what we
were going into,
you fucking knew that!
Ms. Harris, calm down!
Ms. Harris, please, relax!
Please!
Neither of us got
what we wanted, did we?
You knew the risks.
No one must know what happened.
(screaming) Ahh!!!
- Ms. Harris, calm down!
- Ahh!!!
What's wrong with her?
(Christine screaming)
(stomach crunching)
(tense ominous music)
(ooze squelching)
Oh no.
No, no, no, no, no.
No! (grunting)
Congratulations, bitch,
you got exactly
what you fucking wanted!
(Christine screaming)
(flesh squelching)
No! No!
(Christine screaming)
(flesh squelching)
(Julia gasps)
(Christine screaming)
(flesh squelching)
(ominous music)
(Christine screaming continues)
(Christine laughing)
(ominous music continues)
(tentacles squelching)
(Julia gasping)
(Christine laughing continues)
(ominous music rising)
(melancholy music)
(melancholy music continues)